Register of the Richard Paul Mitchell collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Richard Paul Mitchell collection
1906-1983
1950-1960; 1976-1982
77076
Hoover Institution Archives
43 manuscript boxes, 7 oversize boxes, 10 volumes (32.9 linear feet)
Writings, newspapers, magazines, journals, books, clippings, and other printed matter relating to the Muslim Brotherhood, Islamic culture and political movements, and conditions in Islamic countries. Also includes material related to US foreign policy and other global issues from the late 1970s.
Mitchell, Richard Paul, 1925-, collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977, with an increment received in 1986.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1925 June 21 Born, Worcester, Massachusetts
1943-1946 Served in US Marine Corps
1949 Received BA from Clark University Began graduate work at Princeton University in the languages and history of the Near East
1951-1956 Conducted research in Egypt through Fulbright and Ford Foundation grants
1954 Married Alita Mae Jones
1956-1958 Instructor in the Department of Near Eastern Studies at University of Michigan
1958-1962 US Foreign Service officer in Washington, Yemen, and Kuwait
1960 Received PhD from Princeton University with dissertation on the Muslim Brotherhood
1963-1983 Professor of history at University of Michigan
1969 Published The Society of the Muslim Brothers
1973-1975 Served as associate director of the Center for Near Eastern and North African Studies
1983 September 12 Died while conducting research at the American Research Center in Egypt (Cairo)
1984 The Modern Middle East and North Africa, co-authored with Lois A. Aroian, published posthumously
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains material collected by Richard P. Mitchell, a professor and scholar of the history of the modern Middle East and North Africa, during the course of his personal and professional research. A large portion of the collection pertains to the history and the early years of the Muslim Brotherhood, a religious, political, and social organization founded in Egypt in 1928 by Hasan al-Banna. Despite having undergone serious government suppression in 1948, 1954, and 1965, the Muslim Brotherhood remains a large international political organization.
The Society of the Muslim Brothers Research File contains material gathered by Mitchell in Egypt from 1951 to 1956 while conducting research for his dissertation, later published as The Society of the Muslim Brothers by Oxford University Press in 1969. It includes rare publications from members of the Muslim Brotherhood, both official and unofficial, that date from 1934 to 1963. Also included are editions of the organization’s weekly newspaper, Al-Da‘wa; other limited circulation newspapers, including bound volumes of local press; pamphlets mourning the assassination of Hasan al-Banna; and other printed matter regarding the Muslim Brotherhood. In addition, the series contains copies of the journal Al- Muslimūn, which was published by Sa’id Ramadan, a prominent member of the Brotherhood. The items in this series are organized according to an alphanumeric system used and created by Mitchell. An inventory listing the titles of these items is located at the beginning of the series.
The remainder of the collection contains clippings, booklets, books, and other printed matter, mainly from the late 1970s and early 1980s, collected in the course of Mitchell’s work as a professor of history at the University of Michigan and his research leading up to the publication of The Modern Middle East and North Africa. The Geographic File, Subject File, and Arabic File contain Mitchell's newspaper clippings files that he organized by either subject or geographic location. They include clippings from English, French, and Arabic publications and cover topics such as US foreign policy, the Middle East, North Africa, and various other global issues from the late 1970s. These files have been arranged for the most part according to a printed inventory created by Mitchell, located in the Richard P. Mitchell File.
The collection also includes some of Mitchell’s personal writings and correspondence (Richard P. Mitchell File), writings from colleagues and other scholars in the field of Islamic and Middle Eastern studies (Speeches and Writings by Others), newsletters and publications from groups concerned with Middle Eastern and Islamic issues (Organizations File), copies of Arabic publications (Printed Matter and Oversize Material), as well as official US Department of State publications relating to the Middle East and other topics found in the clippings files (Printed Matter).
Related Collection
Richard P. Mitchell collection on the Muslim Brothers (microfilm), Hoover Institution Library
Jam'iyat al-Ikhwan al-Muslimun (Egypt); Civilization, Islamic.; Islam.; Islamic countries.; Islamic literature.; Muslims--Africa.; Philosophy, Islamic.
- Richard P. Mitchell File, 1975-1983, undated (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence, conference materials, writings, and other material related to Richard P. Mitchell, his research, and his work at the University of Michigan. Also includes article summaries completed by Mitchell's student assistants and an index to Mitchell's clippings files. Arranged alphabetically by form, followed by miscellany.
  - Article summaries and progress reports, 1980, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1983, undated
    - General, 1975-1983, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Voll, John C., 1980-1983 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      Includes a typescript copy of a paper by Voll titled, "Islamic Dimensions in Arab Politics since World War II." Voll was the author of the introduction to the 1993 reprint of The Society of Muslim Brothers.
    - Unknown, 1983 August 10 (Box-folder 1: 4)
      Contains a handwritten letter from Mitchell to an unknown recipient, written in Cairo, Egypt shortly before his death. In it Mitchell describes the changes he has observed in the city since he was last there.
  - First Conference of Islamic Philosophy on Islam and Civilization file, 1979 (Box-folder 1: 5-7)
    Includes a notepad with handwritten notes, an invitation, program, conference agenda, and copies of papers presented at the conference. Titles of the papers found in this file include, "Tariq aleaql fi al-turath al'Islami" by Zaki Najib Mahmud, "Islam & Indonesian Culture" by H. A. Mukti Ali, "Iqbal Human Civilization" by S. Jafri, "Problems of Communication between Islamic Civilization & Europe" by N. Daniel, and "Muslim Practice and Modern Development" by Bernd Eisenblätter.
  - Index to geographic and subject files, 1980 July 22 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    Includes cross-references. It should be noted that this index does not include all the files found in the Geographic and Subject Files. In addition, some file names have been modified for clarity.
  - Memo from Jeff Meadowcroft re religious terms and definitions, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Writings, 1980, undated
    - "Les Frères Musulmans," L'Histoire, 1980 September 26 (Box-folder 1: 10)
      Article co-authored with Gilles Kepel.
    - Notes, 1980, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
      Includes index cards with titles of articles and works of interest to Mitchell's research.
  - Miscellany, 1980-1983, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
    Contains a "Stop Israeli Bombing of Lebanon" bumper sticker, a document from "Supporters of the Resistance" regarding an upcoming demonstration, a letter from MERIP requesting donations after their New York office was attacked in 1983, collected correspondence, and a memo regarding the American Research Center in Egypt Fellowships.
- Speeches and Writings by Others, 1968-1983, undated (Boxes 1-2)
  Arranged alphabetically by author or title.
  - Abrahamian, E., "The Crowd in Iranian Politics 1905-1953,", 1968 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Ahmad, Feroz, "The Islamic Assertion in Turkey: Pressures and State Response,", 1981 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Aḥmad, Hasan Makkī Sa‘d, "Al-Ba‘th al-Islāmī al-mu‘āṣir fī Īrān: Judhūruhu wa-taṭawwuruhu (1963-1980)," masters thesis, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 15-16)
  - Ahmed, Akbar S., "Mullah, Mahdi and Mosque: Emergent Trends in Muslim Society,", 1981 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Ansari, Iqbal A., "The Concept of Man in the Quran,", undated (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Ansari, Iqbal A., "Muslim Personal Law in India,", undated (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Arkoun, M., "The Relevance of Contemporary Islam to the Political, Social and Economic Development in North Africa,", 1981 (Box 1: 20)
  - Atherton, Alfred, "Remarks of Alfred Roy Atherton, Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs,", 1977 June 28 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Ayubi, Nazih N. M., "The Political Revival of Islam: The Case of Egypt,", 1980 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Buheiry, Marwan R., "Colonial Scholarship and Muslim Revivalism in 1900,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Caldarola, Carlo, "Fundamentalist Christianity, Israel and the Second Coming,", 1974 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Crowe, Kenneth C., 1975-1976 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    Contains several articles by Crowe published by The Alicia Patterson Foundation. Topics include: policy regarding Saudi Arabia, Middle Eastern oil, the evolution of the Arab corporation, and the Shah of Iran.
  - Davis, Eric, "Ideology, Social Class and Islamic Radicalism in Modern Egypt,", circa 1980 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    Contains Mitchell's handwritten comments and edits in pencil.
  - Davis, Eric, "Religion Against the State: A Comparative Study of Religious Nationalism in Egypt and Israel,", 1982 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    Contains handwritten notes and comments by Mitchell.
  - Foster, Mark, " Libya: The Elusive Revolution [by] Ruth First,", 1983 March 31 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Foster, Mark, " Libya: A Modern History [by] John Wright: A Critical Review,", 1983 February 10 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Goldberg, Elis, "Bases of Traditional Reaction: A Look at the Muslim Brothers,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Hussain, Asaf, "Western Theoretical Approaches to the Political Order of Muslim States: A Critique,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Ibrahim, Saad Eddin, "Anatomy of Egypt's Militant Islamic Groups: Methodological Note and Preliminary Findings,", 1980 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Israeli, Raphael, "The New Wave of Islam,", 1979 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Jameelah, Maryam, "The Call of Islam to Modern Man,", 1975 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Keddie, Nikki R., "Iran: Change in Islam; Islam and Change,", 1980 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Keddie, Nikki R., "Is Khomeini a Fundamentalist?,", 1980 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Kissinger, Henry, "Partial Transcript of an Interview with Kissinger on the State of Western World,", 1974 October 13 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Kizilbash, Hamid H., "The Islamic Conference: Retrospect and Prospect,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Meadowcroft, Jeffrey W., "The Moral Majority,", 1981 April 10 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Powers, Donald LaMoyne, "Bible Prophecy and Israel: Does the Bible Promise Palestine to the Jewish People?,", undated (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Savin, Pierre (pseudonym), "Débats: Israël Vu d’Égypte,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 20)
    Includes a note by the author to Mitchell.
  - Sivan, Emanuel, "Arab Revisionist Historians,", 1978 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Talhami, Ghada, "The Muslim African Experience: Problems and Prospects for the Future,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Tibi, Bassam, "Islamische Weltkonferenz über Islamische Philosop[h]ie,", 1980 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Tibi, Bassam, "The Renewed Role of Islam in the Political and Social Development of the Middle East,", 1983 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Voll, John O., "Islam and Stateness in the Modern Sudan,", 1983 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Voll, John O., "Wahhabism and Mahdism: Parallels and the Current Realities,", 1981 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - "Where Does the Muslim Brother's Movement Stand?,", undated (Box-folder 2: 27)
    Copy of an article in Arabic with a handwritten translation in English.
  - Yapp, M. E., "Contemporary Islamic Revivalism,", 1980 (Box-folder 2: 28)
- The Society of the Muslim Brothers Research Materials, 1934-1963 (Boxes 2-13, 44-49, Volume bound volumes)
  Contains books, pamphlets, and periodicals, mainly from Egypt and Syria, collected by Mitchell as source material for his book The Society of the Muslim Brothers. Many of these publications were written by members of the Muslim Brothers or were official publications produced by the group.
  The bulk of the items in this series are arranged according to an alphanumeric system devised by Mitchell. The first letter stands for the type of item, GR for ghayr rasmī, J for jarīda, M for majalla, R for risāla, and U for eumumi. A detailed inventory of these items, created by Mitchell, is also included and appears at the beginning of the series. It should be noted that not all items listed in the inventory appear in the collection. Items are in Arabic unless otherwise noted.
  - Inventory, undated (Box-folder 2: 29)
    Contains a photocopy of a handwritten inventory of the Arabic books, booklets, periodicals, and other printed matter found in this series. It should be noted that not all material listed in sections J and M appear in the collection. Inventory is written in Arabic with English transliterations.
  - Ghayr rasmī (GR), 1945-1955, undated (Boxes 3-7)
    Contains books in Arabic from the following writers, many of whom were members of the Muslim Brotherhood: Aḥmad Anas al-Hajjājī, ‘Abd al-Khabīr al-Hawalī, Aḥmad al-Sharabāṣī, Muḥammad Shawqī Zakī, ‘Abd al-Hakīm ‘Ābidīn, Muḥammad ‘Abd Allāh Sammān, Fatḥī al-‘Assāl, Al-Bahī al-Khūlī, ‘Abd al-Majīd al-Bājūrī, Muḥyī al-Dīn al-Alwā’ī, ‘Abd al-Raḥmān al-‘Īsawī, ‘Abbās Hāfiẓ, Kāmil Ismā‘īl Sharīf, Al-Sayyid al-Shūrbajī, Muḥammad al-ʻAmāwī, Jamāl al-Dīn ‘Iyyād, ‘Alī Shiḥāta Rizq, Fatḥī ‘Abd al-Hamīd, Muḥammad al-Ghazālī, Muḥammad Quṭb, Sayyid Quṭb,‘Anwar al-Jundī, Aḥmad Anwar al-Jundī, ‘Abd al-Qādir ‘Awda, Muḥammad Labīb al-Būhī, ‘Abd al-Raḥmān al-Bannā, Anwar al-Jundī al-Bannā, ‘Abd al-Bāsiṭ al-Bannā, Sa‘īd Ramaḍān, and Al-Sayyid Sābiq.
    See inventory at the beginning of The Society of Muslim Brothers Research Materials for a more detailed listing of each item.
    - GR-1 - GR-13, 1945-1954, undated (Box 3)
    - GR-14 - GR-28, 1951-1955, undated (Box 4)
    - GR-29 - GR-39, 1951-1954, undated (Box 5)
    - GR-40 - GR-56, 1945-1953, undated (Box 6)
    - GR-57 - GR-65, 1952-1955, undated (Box-folder 7: 1-8)
      No GR-62. GR-63 is listed as GR-62 in handwritten inventory.
  - Jarīda (J), 1950-1956, undated (Boxes 7-8, 44-49)
    Contains Arabic newspapers, including newspapers published by the Muslim Brotherhood and other limited publications; a file of clippings and other printed matter; and a file of material gathered for the appendices to The Society of the Muslim Brothers. Only files J-11 - J-294 listed in Mitchell's inventory appear in the collection.
    - J-11, "Miscellaneous clippings,", 1952-1954, undated (Box-folder 7: 9-10)
      Contains clippings regarding Hasan al-Banna, pamphlets, copies of papers by others, and three issues of the periodical Al-Risāla. Also includes: Shahīd al-jāmi‘a Aḥmad al-Manīsī; Nūr ‘alā al-ṭarīq… by Sa‘īd Ramaḍān, Taqrīr: Jamā‘at al-tabshīr al-Islāmī wa-l-iṣlāḥ bi-l-Sūdān, al-markaz al-‘āmm, Umm Darmān, Al-Quds fī khaṭr bayn al-tahwīd wa-l-tadwīl al-Maktab al-Dā’im li-l-mu’tamar al-Islāmī al-‘āmm, Essentials of Islam: A Moslem Englishman Summarises His Religion by I.C. Evans, al-‘Aqīda wa-shakhṣiyyat rajul al-‘aqīda by ‘Abd al-Ra’ūf, "Facts About the Muslim Brotherhood" by Sa‘id Ramadhan, Min rasā’il al-jamā‘a: ‘Ibād al-raḥmān, al-nashra al-ūlā, “The Obstacles in Our Way” by Hasan al-Banna (typescript translation), al-Rajul al-ilāhī by Aḥmad ‘Abd al-Jawād Sālim, and Al-Shu‘ūb tuqaddim aḍwā’ ‘alā Filasṭīn ilā al-shabāb al-‘Arabī al-nāhiḍ fī dhikr yawm Filasṭīn al-ta’rīkhī 15 Māyū. Material in Arabic, French, and English.
    - J-12, undated (Box-folder 7: 11, Box-folder 8: 1)
      Contains a notebook with writing in English and Arabic, as well as Arabic articles from a folder labeled "appendices." Also includes two collated photocopies of the folder. This file is not described in Mitchell's inventory.
    - J-13 - J-24, Al-Mabāḥith, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 44: 1-5)
    - J-25 - J-35, Al-Ikhwān al-Muslimūn, 1954 (Box-folder 44: 5-8)
    - J-36 - J-53, Al-‘Aṣī, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 44: 8-11)
    - J- 54 - J-58, Minbar al-Sharq, 1950 (Box-folder 48: 1)
    - J-59 - J-217, Al-Da'wa, 1951-1956 (Box-folder 44: 12, Boxes 45-47)
    - J-218 - J-225, Al-Qāhirah, Al-Zamān, and Al-Miṣrī, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 48: 2)
    - J-226 - J-231, Akhbār al-Yawm, 1954 (Box-folder 48: 3)
    - J-232 - J-241, Al-Akhbār, 1954 (Box-folder 48: 4)
    - J-242 - J-254, Al-Ahrām, 1952, 1954 (Box-folder 48: 5-6)
    - J-255 - J-294, Al-Jumhūriyya, 1954 (Box-folder 49: 1-6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 49: 7)
      Contains loose pages that became separated from the above publications.
  - Majalla (M), 1953-1960 (Boxes 8-9)
    Only items M-1 - M-21 listed under the majalla section of Mitchell's inventory are found in the collection. These include copies of Al-Muslimūn, a monthly journal edited by Sa'id Ramadan, a leading member of the Muslim Brotherhood.
    - M-1 - M-12, 1953-1957 (Box-folder 8: 2-13)
    - M-13 - M-21, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 9: 33-41)
  - Risāla (R), 1939-1954, undated (Boxes 9-10)
    Contains books and pamphlets containing official teachings and messages of the Muslim Brotherhood, including writings by the founder of the group, Hasan al-Bannā. Also includes writings by Muṣṭafā al-Sibā ‘ī, Al-Ikhwān al-Muslimūn, Sayyid Quṭb, Hasan al-Huḍaybī, Hasan Shaltūt, ‘Abd al-Mun‘im Aḥmad Ta‘līb, Al-Bahī al-Khūlī, and Sulaymān al-Nadwī. See inventory located at the beginning of this series for a more detailed listing of each item.
    - R-1 - R-26, 1950-1954, undated (Box-folder 9: 1-32, Box-folder 9: 42-43)
    - R-27 - R-60, 1939-1954, undated (Box-folder 10: 1-26, Box-folder 10: 45-47)
  - Eumumi (U), 1934-1956, undated (Boxes 10-13)
    Contains books and printed material by Muḥammad ‘Abd Allāh Sammān, Aḥmad Anas al-Hajjājī, Abū al-A‘lā al-Mawdūdī, Nāṣir al-Dīn al-Albānī al-Sā‘ātī, Mas‘ūd al-Nadwī, Abū al-Hasan al-Nadwī, Kāmil al-Shāfi‘ī, ‘Abd al-Ḥalīm Maḥmūd, Zaynab al-Hakīm, Muḥammad Asad, Anwar al-Sādāt, Yaḥyā Aḥmad al-Darwīrī, Muḥammad ‘Abd al-Mun‘im Khafājī, Aḥmad al-Shirbāṣī, ‘Abd al-Mun‘im Shumays, Muḥammad ‘Alī ‘Alūba Bāshā, Muḥammmad Aḥmad al-‘Adwī, Muḥammad Hasan Aḥmad, ‘Alī ‘Abd al-Rāziq, and Muḥammad Fahmī al-Ṭamāwī. Also included are four volumes of Maḥkamat al-sha‘b (U-27 - U-31), Ha’ulā' hum al-ikhwān (U-39), and two copies of The Moslem Brethren by Isḥāq Mūsā al-Ḥusaynī, one of which is a bound typescript of a translation by John F. Brown (U-49 - U-50).
    - U-1 - U-18, 1950-1954, undated (Box-folder 10: 27-44)
    - U-19 - U-28, 1951-1954, undated (Box 11)
    - U-29 - U-41, 1936-1954, undated (Box 12)
    - U-42 - U-50, 1934-1956, undated (Box-folder 13: 1-9)
  - Bound newspapers, 1955-1963 (Volume volumes)
    All newspapers are in French unless otherwise noted.
    - L'Action, 1955-1956
      Newspaper from Tunisia, later changed to Le Renouveau.
    - L'Action, 1956-1957
    - L'Action, 1957-1958
    - L'Avant Garde, 1959 February-December
    - L'Avant Garde, 1961-1963
      Issues are in French and Arabic.
    - Démocratie, 1957-1958
    - Al-Istiqlal, 1956-1957
      Produced by the political party Hizb Al-Istiqlal in Morocco.
    - Al-Istiqlal, 1959
    - Al-Istiqlal, 1962-1963
    - El Moudjahid, 1958-1962
      Algerian publication in French which began as an information bulletin that was circulated to resistance fighters during the Algerian War.
- Geographic File, 1906-1983, undated (Boxes 13-21)
  Clippings, photocopies of articles, notes, pamphlets, booklets, and other printed matter arranged alphabetically by location. Material mainly in English, with some items in Arabic and French.
  Groupings and file titles are based on Mitchell's index, located in the Richard P. Mitchell File, and his original file names; however, some file names have been modified for clarity. Not all files listed on the index appear in the collection. Also, not all files in the collection are reflected in the index. Files on China, Europe, and USSR originally listed under "Alphabetical Topic File" in Mitchell's index.
  - Arabian Peninsula, 1957-1983, undated
    - Gulf states, 1965-1980 (Box-folder 13: 10)
      Includes an article from Jeune Afrique.
    - Kuwait, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 13: 11)
    - Saudi Arabia, 1973-1981 (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - Yemen, 1973-1980 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Unfiled material, 1957-1983, undated (Box-folder 14: 3)
      Contains materials regarding Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, and the Persian Gulf not yet sorted into subfiles by the collector. Also includes Background Information on Saudi Arabia produced by The Arab Information Center in New York and a poster of a map of Saudi Arabia produced by the Arabian American Oil Company with information on oil as well as different cities and towns in the country.
  - "Beyond the Middle East,", 1972-1980
    - India, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - Philippines, 1972-1980 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1980 (Box-folder 14: 6)
      Contains various articles on other countries that did not necessitate their own file.
  - "Black Africa,", 1972-1980
    - General, 1972-1980 (Box-folder 14: 7)
    - Black Africa - Israel, 1973-1980 (Box-folder 14: 8)
      Contains articles regarding relations between Israel and African states.
    - Drought and food crisis, 1973-1974, 1980 (Box-folder 14: 9)
      Contains articles mainly related to drought and famine which affected the countries of Senegal, Mauritania, Mali, Niger, Chad, and the Upper Volta in 1973 and 1974.
    - East Africa, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 14: 10)
      Contains articles on Ethiopia, Sudan, and Somalia. See also: Egypt
    - Ethiopia, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 14: 11)
      See also: The Horn of Africa
    - The Horn of Africa, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Islam, 1973, 1979 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Uganda, 1973 (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - Central Asia, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 15: 4)
  - China, 1972-1980
    - General, 1978, 1980 (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Relations with Arab World and Africa, 1972, 1978 (Box-folder 15: 6)
      Includes a copy of World Affairs, volume 135, number 2 (Fall 1972).
    - Russian relations, 1973, 1978 (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - Egypt, 1972-1981
    - 1972-1974 (Box-folder 15: 8-9)
    - 1977-1982 (Box-folder 15: 10)
    - Sudan, 1972-1981 (Box-folder 15: 11)
      See also: East Africa
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-1980 (Box-folder 15: 12)
      Includes copies of "Major Trends in the Evolution of the Egyptian National Self-Image: 1900-1950" from Occasional Papers on the Middle East, number 14, and "Annotated Bibliography of the Geo-Political Considerations of Egypt: A Working Prospectus" by Carter Garber, which was written for a history class taught by Mitchell. Also includes several articles from the Egyptian Gazette and the Egyptial Mail.
  - Europe, 1972-1981